<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The soldier's religious exercise in the time of war Being some proper texts, portions of holy scripture, and prayers, useful for those officers and soldiers, who are engaged abroad in Their Majesties service. Publish'd by a late chaplain to the army.</title>
            <author>Late chaplain to the army.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60727</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4430</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219655</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831109</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831109</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35571</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60727)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35571)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2113:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The soldier's religious exercise in the time of war Being some proper texts, portions of holy scripture, and prayers, useful for those officers and soldiers, who are engaged abroad in Their Majesties service. Publish'd by a late chaplain to the army.</title>
                  <author>Late chaplain to the army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Ric. Chiswell, at the Rose and Crown in St. Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC XC. [1690]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an imprimatur leaf dated Jan. 4. 1689.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35571:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35571:1"/>
            <p>THE SOLDIER's Religious Exerciſe IN THE TIME of WAR. BEING Some Proper Texts, Portions of Holy-Scripture, and Prayers, uſeful for thoſe OFFICERS and SOLDIERS, who are engaged abroad in Their Majeſties Service.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſh'd by a late Chaplain to the Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JOSH. 1. 8, 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>This book of the law ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, but thou ſhalt meditate therein day and night, that thou mayeſt obſerve to do according to all that is written therein: for then thou ſhalt make thy way proſperous, and then thou ſhalt have good ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>Have not I commanded thee? Be ſtrong and of a good courage, be not afraid, neither be thou diſmayed; for the Lord thy God is with thee, whitherſoever thou goeſt.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ric. Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. MDCXC.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:35571:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>Jan.</hi> 4. 1689.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:35571:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, and others the chief Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of Their Majeſties Army.</head>
            <p>HAving been ſome time ſince ingaged in the Service of the Army, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered with my ſelf, what courſe would be moſt proper and expedient, to diſcharge the Obligations of the Chaplain's Duty; And (I am of Opinion) That there is no way more uſeful, to his purpoſe, in order to promote the Practical Exerciſe of Religion, among the ordinary and private Soldiers, (who are generally very ignorant of the common Rudiments and Principles of Chriſtianity) than to adviſe the frequent reading of the Holy Scriptures; which indeed, I found by ſad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, was ſhamefully neglected by ſome of them, to the great ſcandal and abuſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. And this I chiefly impute to the want of <hi>Bibles</hi> among them: for I dare ſay, were a ſtrict ſearch and enquiry made in every Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of the Army, we ſhould not find many poſſeſs'd of this Holy Treaſure, which does ſo nearly concern the neceſſary good and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Precious and Immortal Souls. And therefore, to ſupply that defect, or rather the want of Holy Inſtruction from thoſe ſacred
<pb facs="tcp:35571:3"/>Oracles of God's inſpired Word, give me leave, I pray you, to dedicate to your uſe this ſmall <hi>Bible,</hi> or <hi>Summary of Devotional Scripture,</hi> which being of a leſſer ſize, is more fitly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated for the Soldier's carriage, and may be in ſome ſenſe, as uſeful, as it contains a brief Collection of all thoſe neceſſary and pertinent T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xts, which are adapted for a Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier's Chriſtian Duty and Service, in the time of War. And which, as it may ſerve to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the more ignorant and unlearned in the common rules and ways of Salvation; ſo (I hope) it will not altogether prove uſeleſs or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient to remember thoſe who are more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Chriſtian Duty and Calling, that ſo both may become more ſincerely vertuous and Religions towards God, and honeſtly faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſerviceable to the Intereſt of Their Majeſties preſent Government, as they deſire to ſerve the common Rights and Liberties of the Church and Nation. And now I humbly deſire all the chief <hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Commanders</hi> of Their Majeſties Army, (to whoſe fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our I preſent this ſmall <hi>Treati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> or Religious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of <hi>Devotional</hi> Scripture) that they will be pleaſed to give in ſtrict charge or command to all their <hi>ſubalterns,</hi> both Officers and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, that this may be read by them, as they have leiſure and opportunity, either in the <hi>Camp</hi> or <hi>Gariſon;</hi> and eſpecially to thoſe who are engaged in Their Majeſties Service
<pb facs="tcp:35571:3"/>both in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> for whom I have fitted thoſe Holy Collects, or Offices of Morning and Evening Prayer, in the Cloſe of this Book, which will not be improper to be uſed by every particular <hi>Officer</hi> or <hi>Soldier,</hi> who keeps conſtant to the Exerciſe of daily De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion; and beſides, 'tis neceſſary that he do reflect upon ſome of thoſe Holy Paſſages of Scripture, which I have here reduced under ſo many ſeveral Heads, which I judged to be moſt proper for the <hi>Soldier's</hi> Chriſtian Duty, during his Service in the Wars.</p>
            <p>And now, becauſe among the private Men, the Education of ſome is ſo Illiterate, that they cannot Read; I have thought of this expedient to help the ignorant, which is, That his fellow <hi>Soldier</hi> or <hi>Comrade</hi> do by frequent reading in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcate unto his Memory, ſome few of thoſe chief Texts or Portions of Holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>And if theſe Orders and Rules of Religion be ſtrictly obſerved and put in Execution by you, who are the chief <hi>Officers,</hi> you will ſoon find the benefit of this Holy <hi>Diſcipline</hi> to be not only ſerviceable to your ſeives, in keeping your Men orderly and ſober in their Beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>viour; and ſo no leſs quietly ſubmiſſive and obedient to the Words of your Command. But then, what is more happy, this will be in ſome meaſure greatly inſtrumental for the publick. Service of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in reforming thoſe Scandalous Vices and Immoralities of Drunkenneſs and Swearing,
<pb facs="tcp:35571:4"/>which are ſo generally riſen among the more Ignoble and Plebeian ſort. And thus you will come to gain not only the credit of eſteem and Reputation to your ſelves, but you will do no leſs real honour and ſervice to Their Majeſties by your diligence and fidelity in this preſent juncture, wherein we muſt expect either the laſting happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or intire Ruine of the Peace and Proſperity of this Church and Nation; as God is pleaſed to give ſucceſs to Their Majeſties Arms, which (we all know) are now chiefly engaged to maintain the free Exerciſe of our Religion, which is ſo happily modelled according to the excellent Doctrine and Precepts of the Holy <hi>Bible;</hi> And of which this being a ſmall <hi>Epitome,</hi> or Part, I hope it will come the more acceptable for that publick Good and Practical Exerciſe of Holineſs, for which 'tis chiefly intended, for the uſe of thoſe <hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Soldiers,</hi> who are now employ'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in Their Majeſties Service, for the common ſafety and defence of our Religion and Country, and to which I pray <hi>God give a Bleſſing,</hi> that we <hi>may all fight the good fight of faith, to lay hold of eternal life, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35571:4"/>
            <head>THE SOLDIER's Religious Exerciſe IN THE TIME of WAR.</head>
            <div n="1" type="exercise">
               <head>
                  <hi>EXERCISE I.</hi> A Chriſtian Soldier muſt be ſtrictly Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and Religious in his Life and Converſation.</head>
               <p>WHEN the Hoſt goeth forth againſt thine Enemies, then keep thee from every wicked thing, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23. <hi>v.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>For the Lord thy God walketh in the midſt of thy Camp, to deliver thee, and to give up thine Enemies before thee; therefore ſhall thy Camp be Holy, that he ſee no unclean thing in thee, and turn away from thee, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23. <hi>ver.</hi> 14.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:35571:5"/>
               <p>If ye forſake the Lord, and ſerve ſtrange gods, then he will turn, and do you hurt, and conſume you, after that he hath done you good, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24. <hi>ver.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>Be ye therefore very couragious, to keep and do all that is written in the Book of the Law of Moſes, that ye turn not aſide therefrom, to the right hand, or to the left, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 23. <hi>v.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>But cleave unto the Lord your God, as ye have done unto this day, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 23. <hi>v.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>—If thou wilt not hearken unto the voice of the Lord thy God, to obſerve, to do all his commandments, and his ſtatutes, which I command thee this day <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. <hi>v.</hi> 15.</p>
               <p>The Lord ſhall cauſe thee to be ſmitten before thine enemies; thou ſhalt go out one way againſt them, and flee ſeven ways before them, and ſhalt be removed into all the kingdoms of the earth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. <hi>v.</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>And now, Iſrael, what doth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to fear the Lord thy God, to walk in his ways, and to love him, and to ſerve the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>Up, ſanctifie the people, and ſay, Sanctifie your ſelves againſt to morrow: for thus ſaith the Lord God of Iſrael, There is an accurſed thing in the midſt of thee, O Iſrael: thou canſt not ſtand before thine enemies, until ye take away the accurſed thing from among you, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>And you, in any wiſe, keep your ſelves from the accurſed thing, leſt ye make your ſelves accurſed, when ye take of the accurſed thing, and make the camp of Iſrael a curſe, and trouble it, <hi>Joſh</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>Take good heed therefore unto your ſelves, that ye love the Lord your God, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 23. <hi>v.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>Let us hear the concluſion of the whole matter; Fear God, and keep his commandments, for this is the whole duty of man, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 13.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:35571:5"/>
               <p>And the ſoldiers likewiſe demanded of him, ſaying, And what ſhall we do? And he ſaid unto them, Do violence to no man, neither accuſe any falſly, and be content with your wages, <hi>Luke.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>Beſides this, giving all diligence, add to your faith, vertue; and to vertue, knowledge; and to knowledge, temperance; and to temperance, patience; and to patience, godlineſs; and to godlineſs, brotherly kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and to brotherly kindneſs, charity: for if theſe things be in you, and abound, they make you that ye ſhall be neither barren, nor unfruitful in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
               <p>Wherefore the rather, brethren, give diligence to make your calling and election ſure: for if ye do theſe things, ye ſhall never fall, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10.</p>
               <p>The works of the fleſh are manifeſt, which are theſe, adultery, fornication, uncleanneſs, laſciviouſneſs, idolatry, witchcraft, hatred, variance, emulations, wrath, ſtrife, ſeditions, hereſies, envyings, murders, drunkenneſs, revilings, and ſuch like: they which do ſuch things, ſhall not inherit the kingdom of God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19, 20, 21, 22.</p>
               <p>But as he which hath called you is holy, ſo be ye holy in all manner of converſation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 15.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="exercise">
               <head>
                  <hi>EXERCISE II.</hi> A Chriſtian Soldier muſt exerciſe the Acts of daily Repentance, by hearty Contrition, ſorrow ful Confeſſion, and the ſincere Reſolution of Holy amendment for the time to come.</head>
               <p>HAve mercy upon me, O God, according to thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindneſs, according unto the multitude of thy mercies, blot out my tranſgreſſions, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51. <hi>v.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Waſh me throughly from my iniquity, and cleanſe me from my ſin, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51. <hi>v.</hi> 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:35571:6"/>
               <p>For I acknowledge my tranſgreſſions, and my ſin is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver before me.</p>
               <p>Hide thy face from my ſins, and blot out all mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51. <hi>v.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>Create in me a clean heart, O God, and renew a right ſpirit within me, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51 <hi>v.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>The ſacrifices of God are a broken ſpirit, a broken and a contrite heart, O God, thou wilt not deſpiſe, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51.17.</p>
               <p>Deliver me then, O God, from blood guiltineſs, from the ſins of malice and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs, of whoredom and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, of murmuring and diſobedience, of ſwearing and profanation of thy name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Here recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the ſins you are guilty of.</note> thou God of my ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51. <hi>v.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>I have ſinned, what ſhall I do unto thee, O thou preſerver of men? <hi>Job</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>— I ſaid, I will confeſs my tranſgreſſions unto the Lord, and thou forgaveſt the iniquity of my ſin</p>
               <p>For this ſhall every one, that is godly, pay unto thee, in a time, when thou mayeſt be found, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.5, 6.</p>
               <p>If we confeſs our ſins, he is faithful and juſt to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us our ſins, and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9.</p>
               <p>Bring forth therefore fruits meet for repentance, — <hi>Luk.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>Repent and be converted, that your ſins may be blotted out, when the times of refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.19.</p>
               <p>Sin no more, leſt a worſe thing come unto thee, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.14.</p>
               <p>God having raiſed up his ſon Jeſus, ſent him to bleſs you, in turning away every one of you from his iniquities, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.26.</p>
               <p>I beſeech you therefore, brethren, by the mercies of God, that ye preſent your bodies a living ſacrifice, holy, acceptable unto God, which is your reaſonable ſervice.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:35571:6"/>
               <p>And be not conformed to this world, but be ye tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the renewing of your mind, that ye may prove what is that good, and acceptable, and perfect will of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="exercise">
               <head>
                  <hi>EXERCISE III.</hi> A Chriſtian Soldier muſt meditate upon the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite love and goodneſs of God, in giving his Son to be the Saviour of the World.</head>
               <p>THis is a faithful ſaying, and worthy of all accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, That Chriſt Jeſus came into the world to ſave ſinners, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15.</p>
               <p>So God loved the world, that he gave his only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſon: that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life, St. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16.</p>
               <p>John ſeeth Jeſus coming unto him, and ſaith, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the lamb of God, which taketh away the ſins of the world, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.29.</p>
               <p>He was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, he was bruiſed for our iniquities; the chaſtiſement of our peace was upon him, and with his ſtripes we are healed, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 53.5.</p>
               <p>To him give all the prophets witneſs, that through his name whoſoever believeth in him, ſhall receive remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſins, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.43.</p>
               <p>God commendeth his love towards us, in that while we were yet ſinners, Chriſt died for us.</p>
               <p>Much more then being now juſtified by his blood, we ſhall be ſaved from wrath through him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 8, 9.</p>
               <p>And if any man ſin, we have an advocate with the Father Jeſus Chriſt the righteous; and he is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for our ſins, and not for ours only, but alſo for the ſins of the whole world, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="exercise">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:35571:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>EXERCISE IV.</hi> A Chriſtian Soldier muſt exerciſe himſelf in a conſtant and babitual Preparation for Death, conſidering the many fatal Accidents and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, to which his life is expoſed in the time of War.</head>
               <p>O That they were wiſe, that they underſtood this, that they would conſider their latter end, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. <hi>v.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>Whereas ye know not what ſhall be on the morrow: for what is your life? it is even a vapour that appeareth for a little time, and then vaniſheth away, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.14.</p>
               <p>Surely men of low degree are vanity, and men of high degree are alike, to be laid in the balance, they are altogether lighter than vanity, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 62.9.</p>
               <p>Seeing his days are determined, the number of his months are with thee, thou haſt appointed his bounds that he cannot paſs, <hi>Job</hi> 14.5.</p>
               <p>So teach us to number our days, that we may apply our hearts unto wiſdom, <hi>Pſ</hi> 90.12.</p>
               <p>— All the days of my appointed time will I wait, till my change come.</p>
               <p>For now thou numbereſt my ſteps, doſt thou not watch over my ſin? <hi>Job</hi> 14.14, 16.</p>
               <p>God will not caſt away a perfect man — <hi>Job</hi> 8.20.</p>
               <p>Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright: for the end of that man is peace, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 37.37.</p>
               <p>Rejoice not againſt me, O mine enemy: when I fall, I ſhall ariſe; when I ſit in darkneſs, the Lord ſhall be a light unto me, <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.8.</p>
               <p>Why art thou caſt down, O my ſoul, and why art thou diſquieted in me? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.5.</p>
               <p>I have ſet the Lord always before me; becauſe he is at my right hand, I ſhall not be moved.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:35571:7"/>
               <p>Thou wilt ſhew me the path of life: in thy preſence is fulneſs of joy, at thy right hand there are pleaſures for evermore, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 8, 11.</p>
               <p>For which cauſe we faint not, but though our outward man periſh, yet the inward man is renewed day by day.</p>
               <p>While we look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen: for the things which are ſeen are temporal, but the things which are not ſeen are eternal, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16, 18.</p>
               <p>Therefore being juſtified by faith, we have peace with God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>By whom alſo we have acceſs by faith into this grace, wherein we ſtand, and rejoice in hope of the glory of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2.</p>
               <p>I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the Faith.</p>
               <p>Henceforth there is laid up for me a crown of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, which the Lord the righteous Judge ſhall give me at that day; and not to me only, but unto them alſo which love his appearing, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7, 8.</p>
               <p>— Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, from henceforth, yea, ſaith the ſpirit, that they may reſt from their labours. and their works do follow them, <hi>Rev</hi> 14.13.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed is that ſervant, whom his lord when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, ſhall find ſo doing, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.46.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="exercise">
               <head>
                  <hi>EXERCISE V.</hi> A Chriſtian Soldier muſt give all due ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and obedience to the Commands of his chief Officer or Leader, and the Officer muſt be no leſs faithful and diligent in his Truſt.</head>
               <p>AND Moſes ſaid unto them, If ye will do this thing, if ye will go armed before the Lord to war, <hi>Numb.</hi> 32.20.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:35571:8"/>
               <p>And will go all of you armed over Jordan before the Lord, until he hath driven out his enemies from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, <hi>Numb.</hi> 32. <hi>v.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>And the land be ſubdued before the Lord: then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ye ſhall return, and be guiltleſs before the Lord, and before Iſrael, and this land ſhall be your poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion before the Lord, <hi>Numb.</hi> 32.22.</p>
               <p>But if ye will not do ſo, behold ye have ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord, and be ſure your ſin will find you out, <hi>Numb</hi> 32.23.</p>
               <p>And the children of Gad, and the children of Reu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben ſpake unto Moſes, ſaying, Thy ſervants will do as my Lord commandeth, <hi>Numb.</hi> 32.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</p>
               <p>Thy ſervants will paſs over, every man armed for war, before the Lord, to battle, as my lord ſaith. <hi>Numb.</hi> 32. <hi>v.</hi> 27.</p>
               <p>And they anſwered Joſhua, ſaying, All that thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeſt us, we will do, and whitherſoever thou ſendeſt us, we will go, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1. <hi>v</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>According as we hearkened unto Moſes in all things, ſo will we hearken unto thee, only the Lord thy God be with thee, as he was with Moſes, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever he be that doth rebel againſt thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, and will not hearken unto thy words, in all that thou commandeſt him, he ſhall be put to death; only be ſtrong and of good courage, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>And the officers which were over thouſands of the hoſt, the captains of thouſands, and cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ains of hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, came near unto Moſes, <hi>Numb.</hi> 31.48.</p>
               <p>And they ſaid unto Moſes, Thy ſervants have taken the ſum of the men of war, which are under our charge, and there lacketh not one man of us, <hi>Numb.</hi> 31.49.</p>
               <p>And there came of the children of Benjamin and Judah to the Hold unto David, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.16.</p>
               <p>And David went out to meet them, and anſwered and ſaid unto them, If ye be come peaceably unto me, to help me, mine heart ſhall be kind unto you; but if ye be come to betray me to mine enemies, ſeeing there is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35571:8"/>no wrong in mine hands, the God of our fathers look thereon, and rebuke it, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.17.</p>
               <p>Then the ſpirit came upon Amaſai, who was chief of the captains, and he ſaid, Thine are we, David, and on thy ſide, thou ſon of Jeſſe; peace, peace be unto thee, and peace be to thine helpers, for thy God helpeth thee. Then David received them, and made them cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of the band, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.18.</p>
               <p>And they helped David againſt the band of the ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, for they were all mighty men of valour, and were captains in the hoſt, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.21.</p>
               <p>All theſe men of war, that could keep rank, came with a perfect heart to Hebron, to make David king over all Iſrael: and all the reſt alſo of Iſrael were of one heart to make David king, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.38.</p>
               <p>For I alſo am a man, ſet under authority, having un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der me ſoldiers; and I ſay unto one, Go, and he goeth; and to another, Come, and he cometh; and to my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, Do this, and he doth it, <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.8.</p>
               <p>Exhort ſervants to be obedient unto their own maſters, and to pleaſe them well in all things, not anſwering a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.9.</p>
               <p>Not purloyning, but ſhewing all good fidelity, that they may adorn the doctrine of God our ſaviour in all things, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.10.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="exercise">
               <head>
                  <hi>EXERCISE VI.</hi> A Soldier muſt exerciſe his Valour and Courage for the Cauſe of God, and fight for the Defence of his Religion and Country.</head>
               <p>— BE thou valiant, and fight the Lord's battles, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.17.</p>
               <p>Be of good courage, and let us play the men for our people, and for the cities of our God; and the Lord do that which ſeemeth him good, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.12.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:35571:9"/>
               <p>And Joab drew nigh, and the people that were with him, unto the battle againſt the Syrians; and they fled before him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.13.</p>
               <p>— For the battel is the Lord's, and he will give you into our hands, 1 <hi>Sam</hi> 17.47.</p>
               <p>For the Lord your God is he, that goeth with you, to fight for you againſt your enemies to ſave you, <hi>Deut.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 4</p>
               <p>When thou goeſt out to battel againſt thine enemies, and ſeeſt horſes, and chariots, and a people more than thou, be not afraid of them: for the Lord thy God is with thee — <hi>Deut.</hi> 20.1.</p>
               <p>Through God we ſhall do valiantly: for he it is that ſhall tread down our enemies, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 60.12.</p>
               <p>The right hand of the Lord is exalted, the right hand of the Lord doeth valiantly, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 118.16.</p>
               <p>Finally, my brethren, be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>Wherefore take unto you the whole armour of God, that ye may be able to withſtand in the evil day — <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.13.</p>
               <p>Fight the good fight of faith, lay hold on eternal life—1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.12.</p>
               <p>Thou therefore endure hardneſs, as a good ſoldier of Jeſus Chriſt, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3.</p>
               <p>— For the time would fail me to tell of Gedeon, and of Barack, and of Samſon, and of Jephtha, of David alſo, and of Samuel the prophets, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.32.</p>
               <p>Who through faith ſubdued kingdoms, wrought righteouſneſs, obtained promiſes, ſtopped the mouths of lions, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.33.</p>
               <p>Quenched the violence of fire, eſcaped the edge of the ſword, out of weakneſs were made ſtrong, waxed valiant in fight, turned to flight the armies of aliens, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.34.</p>
               <p>Fear none of thoſe things which thou ſhalt ſuffer — be thou faithful unto death, and I will give thee a crown of life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="exercise">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:35571:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>EXERCISE VII.</hi> A good Soldier muſt exerciſe his Chriſtian hope and confidence in the ſtrength and power of God, and not truſt in the Arm of Fleſh.</head>
               <p>THE Lord is my light and my ſalvation, whom ſhall I fear? The Lord is the ſtrength of my life, of whom ſhall I be afraid? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.1.</p>
               <p>When the wicked, even mine enemies and my foes came upon me to eat up my fleſh, they ſtumbled and fell, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.2.</p>
               <p>Though an hoſt ſhould encamp againſt me, my heart ſhall not fear; though war ſhould riſe againſt me, in this will I be confident, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.3.</p>
               <p>—The God of Iſrael is he, that giveth ſtrength and power unto his people: bleſſed be God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.35.</p>
               <p>Be ſtrong and couragious, be not afraid nor diſmayed for the king of Aſſyria; nor for all the multitude that is with him: for there be mo with us, than with him, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32. <hi>v.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>With him is an arm of fleſh, but with us is the Lord our God, to help us, and to fight our battels — 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32. <hi>v.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>There is no king ſaved by the multitude of an hoſt, a mighty man is not delivered by much ſtrength, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.16.</p>
               <p>An horſe is a vain thing for ſafety; neither ſhall he deliver any by his great ſtrength, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33. <hi>v.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>For I will not truſt in my bow; neither ſhall my ſword ſave me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.6.</p>
               <p>But thou haſt ſaved us from our enemies, and haſt put them to ſhame that hated us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.7.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:35571:10"/>
               <p>Then ſaid David to the Philiſtin, Thou comeſt to me with a ſword, and with a ſpear, and with a ſhield: but I come to thee in the name of the Lord of hoſts the God of the armies of Iſrael — 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.45.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed be the Lord my ſtrength, which teacheth my hands to war, and my fingers to fight, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144. <hi>v.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>My goodneſs and my fortreſs, my high tower and my deliverer, my ſhield, and he in whom I truſt, who ſubdueth my people under me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144. <hi>v.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Behold, God is my ſalvation, I will truſt, and not be afraid, for the Lord Jehovah is my ſtrength, and my ſong, he alſo is become my ſalvation, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord, Curſed be man that truſteth in man, and maketh fleſh his arm, and whoſe heart departeth from the Lord, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.5.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed is the man that truſteth in the Lord, and whoſe hope the Lord is, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17. <hi>v.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>— Be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might, <hi>Epheſ</hi> 6.10.</p>
               <p>Be of good courage, and he ſhall ſtrengthen your heart, all ye that hope in the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.24.</p>
               <p>He hath ſhewed ſtrength with his arm, he hath ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred the proud in the im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gination of their hearts, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.51.</p>
               <p>Let thy mercy (O Lord) be upon us; according as we hope in thee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.22.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="exercise">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:35571:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>EXERCISE VIII.</hi> The Chriſtian Soldier muſt then firmly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the Promiſes of God's help, when he is to engage the Enemy in Battel.</head>
               <p>AND Moſes ſaid unto the people, Fear ye not, ſtand ſtill, and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord, which he will ſhew you to day — <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13.</p>
               <p>The Lord ſhall fight for you, and ye ſhall hold your peace, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.14.</p>
               <p>— Hear, O Iſrael, you approach this day unto battel againſt your enemies: let not your hearts faint, fear not, and do not tremble, neither be ye terrified becauſe of them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 20.3.</p>
               <p>For the Lord your God is he, that goeth with you, to fight for you againſt your enemies to ſave you; ye ſhall not need to fight in this battel; ſet your ſelves, ſtand ye ſtill, and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord with you, O Judah and Jeruſalem, fear not, nor be diſmayed, to morrow go out againſt them, for the Lord will be with you — 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>And they roſe early in the morning, and went forth into the wilderneſs of Tekoa: and as they went forth, Jehoſaphat ſtood, and ſaid, Hear me, O Judah, and ye inhabitants of Jeruſalem: Believe in the Lord your God, ſo ſhall ye be eſtabliſhed: believe his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, ſo ſhall ye proſper, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>Were not the Ethiopians, and the Lubims a huge hoſt, with very many chariots and horſemen? yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou didſt rely on the Lord, he delivered them into thine hand, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>For the eyes of the Lord run to and fro through the whole earth, to ſhew himſelf ſtrong in the behalf of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35571:11"/>them, whoſe heart is perfect towards him— 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>I will lift up mine eyes unto the hills: from whence cometh my help, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121.1.</p>
               <p>My help cometh from the Lord, which made heaven and earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121.2.</p>
               <p>Fear thou not, for I am with thee: be not diſmayed, for I am thy God: I will ſtrengthen thee, yea, I will help thee; yea, I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righteouſneſs, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.10.</p>
               <p>Behold, all they that were incenſed againſt thee, ſhall be aſhamed and confounded: they ſhall be as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and they that ſtrive with thee ſhall periſh, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.11.</p>
               <p>And it ſhall come to paſs, that whoſoever ſhall call on the name of the Lord, ſhall be delivered: for in mount Zion, and in Jeruſalem ſhall be deliverance, as the Lord hath ſaid, — <hi>Joel</hi> 2.32.</p>
               <p>— And they ſhall never periſh, neither ſhall any pluck them out of my hand, <hi>John</hi> 10.28.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, the foundation of God ſtandeth ſure, having this ſeal, The Lord knoweth them that are his — 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19.</p>
               <p>Wherein God willing more abundantly to ſhew un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heirs of promiſe, the immutability of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, confirmed it by an oath, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17.</p>
               <p>That by two immutable things, in which it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for God to lie, we might have a ſtrong conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who have fled for refuge to lay hold upon the hope ſet before us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="exercise">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:35571:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>EXERCISE IX.</hi> A devout Soldier muſt exerciſe the duty of Prayer before he goes upon Action, or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to fight his Enemies in Battel.</head>
               <p>AND the children of Iſrael ſaid unto the Lord, We have ſinned, do thou unto us whatſoever ſeemeth good unto thee, deliver us only, we pray thee, this day, <hi>Judg.</hi> 10.15.</p>
               <p>And Sampſon called unto the Lord, and ſaid, O Lord God, remember me, I pray thee, and ſtrengthen me, I pray thee, only this once, O God — <hi>Judg.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 28.</p>
               <p>I will call on the Lord, who is worthy to be praiſed: ſo ſhall I be ſaved from mine enemies, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22. <hi>v.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>And Aſa cried unto the Lord his God, and ſaid, Lord, it is nothing with thee to help, whether with many, or with them that have no power: help us, O Lord our God, for we reſt on thee, and in thy name we go againſt this multitude: O Lord, thou art our God, let not man prevail againſt thee, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>So the Lord ſmote the Ethiopians before Aſa, and before Judah, and the Ethiopians fled, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>And when Judah looked back, behold, the battel was before and behind; and they cried unto the Lord, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.14.</p>
               <p>Then the men of Judah gave a ſhout, and as the men of Judah ſhouted, it came to paſs, that God ſmote Jeroboam, and all Iſrael before Abijah and Judah, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 15.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:35571:12"/>
               <p>And the Children of Iſrael fled before Judah: and God delivered them into their hand, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>Plead my cauſe (O Lord) with them that ſtrive with me: fight againſt them that fight againſt me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35. <hi>v.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Take hold of ſhield and buckler, and ſtand up for mine help, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35. <hi>v.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Draw out alſo the ſpear, and ſtop the way againſt them that perſecute me: ſay unto my ſoul, I am thy ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35. <hi>v.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>As for me, I will call upon God; and the Lord ſhall ſave me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. <hi>v.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>Evening, and morning, and at noon day, will I pray, and cry aloud, and he ſhall hear my voice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. <hi>v.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>He hath delivered my ſoul in peace, from the battel that was againſt me — <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. <hi>v.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>The Lord is nigh unto all them that call upon him; to all that call upon him in truth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.18.</p>
               <p>He will fulfil the deſire of them that fear him: he alſo will hear their cry, and will ſave them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. <hi>v.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>But it came to paſs, that when Sanballat, and Tobiah, and the Arabians, and the Ammonites, and the Aſhdo dites heard that the walls of Jeruſa em were made up and that the breaches began to be ſtopped, then they were very wroth, <hi>Neh.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>And conſpired all of them together, to come and to fight againſt Jeruſalem, and to hinder it, <hi>Neh.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, we made our prayer unto our God, and ſet a watch againſt them day and night, becauſe of them, <hi>Neh.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>And he ſpake a parable unto them, to this end, that men ought always to pray, and not to faint, <hi>Luke</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>— Verily, verily, I ſay unto you, Whatſoever ye ſhall ask the Father in my name, he will give it you, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 23.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:35571:12"/>
               <p>Be careful for nothing; but in every thing by prayer and ſupplication with thankſgiving, let your requeſts be made known unto God, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6.</p>
               <p>— The effectual fervent prayer of a righteous man availeth much, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.16.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="exercise">
               <head>
                  <hi>EXERCISE X.</hi> A Chriſtian Soldier muſt not fear his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but pray for happy Deliverance and Victory.</head>
               <p>AND Moſes ſaid unto the people, Fear ye not, ſtand ſtill, and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord, which he will ſhew you to day, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13.</p>
               <p>Be ſtrong and of a good courage, fear not, nor be afraid of them: for the Lord thy God, he it is that doth go with thee, he will not fail thee, nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thee, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31. <hi>v.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>And the Lord ſaid unto Joſhua, Fear them not: for I have delivered them into thine hand; there ſhall not a man of them ſtand before thee, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>And Joſhua ſaid unto them, Fear not, nor be diſmayed, be ſtrong; and of good courage: for thus ſhall the Lord do to all your enemies againſt whom ye fight, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>O our God, wilt not thou judge them? for we have no might againſt this great company that cometh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us; neither know we what to do, but our eyes are upon thee, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>And he ſaid, Hearken ye, all Judah, and ye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of Jeruſalem, and thou king Jehoſaphat, Thus ſaith the Lord unto you, be not afraid, nor diſmayed by reaſon of this great multitude, for the battel is not yours, but Gods, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 15.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:35571:13"/>
               <p>To morrow go ye down againſt them — 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>Ye ſhall not need to fight in this battel: ſet your ſelves, ſtand ye ſtill, and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord with you, O Judah and Jeruſalem: fear not, nor be diſmayed; to morrow go out againſt them, for the Lord will be with you, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.17.</p>
               <p>And they roſe early in the morning, and went forth into the wilderneſs of Tekoa: and as they went forth, Jehoſhaphat ſtood, and ſaid, Hear me, O Judah, and ye inhabitants of Jeruſalem, believe in the Lord your God, ſo ſhall ye be eſtabliſhed, believe his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, ſo ſhall ye proſper, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>My times are in thy hand: deliver me from the hand of mine enemies, and from them that perſecute me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.15.</p>
               <p>Deliver me from mine enemies, O my God: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend me from them that riſe up againſt me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59. <hi>v.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Deliver me from the workers of iniquity, and ſave me from bloody men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 59. <hi>v.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Thou art my king, O God: command deliverances for Jacob, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44. <hi>v.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Through thee will we puſh down our enemies; through thy name will we tread them under that riſe up againſt us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44. <hi>v.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Be not afraid of their faces: for I am with thee, to deliver thee, ſaith the Lord, <hi>Jer.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>And fear not them which kill the body — <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 28.</p>
               <p>Brethren, my hearts deſire and prayer to God for Iſrael, is, that they might be ſaved, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.1.</p>
               <p>— For he hath ſaid, I will never leave thee nor forſake thee, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5.</p>
               <p>So that we may boldly ſay, The Lord is my helper, and I will not fear what man ſhall do unto me, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 6.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="exercise">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:35571:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>EXERCISE XI.</hi> If our Forces become weakned, and the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my grows ſtrong and powerful, we muſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our Souls, and pray more earneſtly, that God may avert the Judgement of the Sword which is ſent to puniſh the ſins of the Nation.</head>
               <p>EVen all Nations ſhall ſay, Wherefore hath the Lord done thus unto this land? what meaneth the heat of this great anger? <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.24.</p>
               <p>Then men ſhall ſay, Becauſe they have forſaken the covenant of the Lord God of their fathers — <hi>Deut</hi> 29. <hi>v.</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>Up, ſanctifie the people, and ſay, Sanctifie your ſelves againſt to morrow: for thus ſaith the Lord God of Iſrael, There is an accurſed thing in the midſt of thee, O Iſrael: thou canſt not ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thine enemies, until ye take away the accurſed thing from among you, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.13.</p>
               <p>If my people which are called by my name, ſhalt humble themſelves, and pray, and ſeek my face, and turn from their wicked ways: then will I hear from heaven, and will forgive their ſin, and heal their land, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.14.</p>
               <p>O remember not againſt us former iniquities; let thy tender mercies ſpeedily prevent us: for we are brought very low, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79. <hi>v.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>Help us, O God of our ſalvation, for the glory of thy name, and deliver us, and purge away our ſins for thy names ſake, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79. <hi>v.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>O Lord God of Iſrael, thou art righteous, for we remain yet eſcaped, as it is this day: behold, we are before thee in our treſpaſſes: for we cannot ſtand before thee, becauſe of this, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 15.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:35571:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:35571:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:35571:15"/>
               <p>I looked on my right hand, and beheld, but there was no man that would know me, refuge failed me: no man cared for my ſoul, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 142. <hi>v.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Attend unto my cry, for I am brought very low, deliver me from my perſecutors: for they are ſtronger than I, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 142. <hi>v.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, thou art juſt in all that is brought upon us: for thou haſt done right, but we have done wickedly, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 33.</p>
               <p>Neither have our kings, our princes, our prieſts, nor our fathers kept thy law, nor hearkened unto thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and thy teſtimonies, wherewith thou didſt teſtifie againſt them. <hi>Neh.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 34.</p>
               <p>For they have not ſerved thee in their kingdom, and in thy great goodneſs that thou gaveſt them, and in the large and far land which thou gaveſt before them, neither turned they from their wicked works, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 35.</p>
               <p>Help us, O God of our ſalvation, for the glory of thy name <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79. <hi>v.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>O Lord, be gracious unto us, we have waited for thee: be thou their arm every morning, our ſalvation alſo in the time of trouble, <hi>Iſal.</hi> 33. <hi>v.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Be not far from me, for trouble is near; for there is none to help, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. <hi>v.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>Deliver my ſoul from the ſword—<hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. <hi>v.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>O our God, wilt thou not judge them? for we have no might againſt this great company that cometh againſt us: neither know we what to do, but our eyes are upon thee, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>Humble your ſelves therefore under the mighty hand of God, that he may exalt you in due time, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.6.</p>
               <p>The God of all grace, who hath called us unto his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal glory by Chriſt Jeſus, after that ye have ſuffered a while, make you perfect, ſtabliſh, ſtrengthen, ſettle you, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>And after all that is come upon us for our evil deeds, and for our great treſpaſs, ſeeing that thou our God haſt puniſhed us leſs than our iniquities deſerve, and haſt given us ſuch deliverance as this, <hi>Ezza</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 13.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:35571:15"/>
               <p>Should we again break thy commandments, and joyn in affinity with the people of theſe abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations? wouldeſt thou not be angry with us, till thou haſt conſumed us, ſo that there ſhould be no remnant, nor eſcaping? <hi>Err.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 14.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="exercise">
               <head>
                  <hi>EXERCISE XII.</hi> But if it pleaſe God to bleſs our Forces with happy Victory and Succeſs; then let all the Officers and Soldiers of the Army, and all the People of the Land, aſcribe the Power and Glory to the Lord, and devoutly ſay,</head>
               <p>HAppy art thou, O Iſrael: who is like unto thee, O people: ſaved by the Lord the ſhield of thy help, and who is the ſword of thine excellency! and thine enemies ſhall be found liers unto thee, and thou ſhalt tread upon their high places, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33. <hi>v.</hi> 29.</p>
               <p>Thy right hand is become glorious in power, thy right hand hath daſhed in pieces the enemy, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>And in the greatneſs of thine excellency, thou haſt overthrown them that roſe up againſt thee — <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>Who is like unto thee, O Lord, amongſt the Gods? who is like thee, glorious in holineſs, fearful in praiſes, doing wonders? <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>Not unto us, O Lord, not unto us, but unto thy name give glory: for thy mercy, and for thy truths ſake, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.1.</p>
               <p>He aroſe, and ſmote the Philiſtins until his hand was weary, and his hand clave unto the ſword: and the Lord wrought a great victory that day — 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. <hi>v.</hi> 10.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:35571:16"/>
               <p>Rejoice, O ye nations, with his people, for he will avenge the blood of his ſervants, and will ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vengeance to his adverſaries, and will be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to his land, and to his people, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.43.</p>
               <p>The eternal God is thy refuge, and underneath are the everlaſting arms: and he ſhall thruſt out the enemy from before thee, and ſhall ſay, Deſtroy them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. <hi>v.</hi> 27.</p>
               <p>Thanks be to God which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.57.</p>
               <p>O ſing unto the Lord a new ſong, for he hath done marvellous things: his right hand, and his holy arm hath gotten him the victory, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 98. <hi>v.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Wherefore David bleſſed the Lord before all the congregation: and David ſaid, Bleſſed be thou, Lord God of Iſrael, our father, for ever and ever, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. <hi>v.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>Thine, O Lord, is the greatneſs, and the power, and the glory, and the victory, and the majeſty; for all that is in the heaven and in the earth, is thine: thine is the kingdom, O Lord, and thou art exalted as head above all, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. <hi>v.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>Both riches and honour come of thee, and thou reigneſt over all, and in thine hand is power and might, and in thine hand it is to make great, and to give ſtrength unto all, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. <hi>v.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>Now therefore our God, we thank thee and praiſe thy glorious name, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.13.</p>
               <p>—For thine is the kingdom, and the power, and the glory for ever. Amen. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.13.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="collects_and_prayers">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:35571:16"/>
            <head>Some <hi>COLLECTS</hi> proper for the Exerciſe of the Soldier's Morning and Evening Service, of Private Devotion, in the Camp or Gariſon.</head>
            <div n="1" type="collect">
               <head>
                  <hi>COLLECT I.</hi> For God's aſſiſtance in Prayer.</head>
               <p>LET thy merciful ears, O Lord, be open to the Prayers of thy humble ſervant; and that I may obtain my Petitions, make me to ask ſuch things as ſhall pleaſe thee, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt my Lord. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="collect">
               <head>
                  <hi>COLLECT II.</hi> Of Contrition and Confeſſion.</head>
               <p>ALmighty and Everlaſting God, who hateſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that thou haſt made, and doeſt forgive the ſins of all them that are truly penitent; create and make in me a new and contrite heart, that I
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35571:17"/>worthily lamenting my ſins, and acknowledging my wretchedneſs, may obtain of thee, the God of all mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, perfect remiſſion and forgiveneſs, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="collect">
               <head>
                  <hi>COLLECT III.</hi> For God's free Pardon and Abſolution.</head>
               <p>ALmighty God our heavenly Father, who of thy great goodneſs haſt promiſed forgiveneſs of ſins to all them that with hearty repentance and true Faith turn unto thee; have mercy upon me, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and deliver me from all my ſins, confirm and ſtrengthen me in all grace and holineſs, and bring me unto everlaſting life, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="collect">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>ALmighty and everlaſting God, I beſeech thee to abſolve me from all mine offences, that through thy mercy in Chriſt Jeſus, I may be delivered from the bonds of thoſe ſins, which by my frailty I have committed; Grant this, O heavenly Father, for Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt his ſake, our bleſſed Lord and Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="collect">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:35571:17"/>
               <head>COLLECT IV. <hi>For Grace.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>[Note, That this Collect is for the Morning.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord our heavenly Father, Almighty and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting God, who haſt ſafely brought me to the beginning of this day, defend me in the ſame with thy mighty power, and grant that I may fall into no ſin, neither run into any kind of danger; but that all my thoughts, words and actions may be ordered by thy governance, to do alwaies that is righteous in thy fight, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="collect">
               <head>
                  <hi>COLLECT V.</hi> For aid againſt Perils.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>[Note, That this Collect is to be ſaid at Night.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>LIghten mine eyes, O Lord, that I ſleep not in darkneſs, nor in the ſhadow of death; but by thy great mercy defend me from all perils and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers this night, that the Enemy may have no advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage over me, nor yet the wicked approach to hurt me; but preſerve me both in body and ſoul, through Jeſus Chriſt my Lord and Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="collect">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:35571:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>COLLECT VI.</hi> For a Bleſſing upon the Church and State.</head>
               <p>O Lord look down from Heaven, behold and viſit us with thy Salvation, have mercy upon theſe ſinful and diſtracted Kingdoms, pardon our great and crying ſins, divert thy Judgments; and give us all grace thankfully to accept thy mercies: defend this Church with thy continual help and government: Bleſs and preſerve Their Majeſties King WILLIAM and Queen MARY, proſper Their Forces with all happineſs, both by Sea and Land, and make them eminent Inſtruments of doing good for the further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of thy glory; and do thou at laſt bring Them to thy everlaſting Kingdom, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord and Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="collect">
               <head>
                  <hi>COLLECT V.</hi> For Victory over our Enemies.</head>
               <p>O God the protector of all them that truſt in thee, the Lord of all power and might, be ready, I beſeech thee, to ſave and deliver me, and all my Superior Officers and fellow Soldiers of this <note n="†" place="margin">This to be uſed as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</note> Camp or Gariſon from the hands of our Enemies, that we may be preſerved and comforted in all the dangers and Calamities of War: do thou ſtrengthen the hands of our General, and go along with our Officers and Soldiers, and ſtand by us all in the day of Battel, that we being armed by the power of thy Divine Providence, may do great
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35571:18"/>and valiant Acts, and ſo magnifie thy honour and glory in giving us Victory and deliverance, through Jeſus Chriſt our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="collect">
               <head>
                  <hi>COLLECT VI.</hi> For the Peace of the Chriſtian World.</head>
               <p>GRant, I beſeech thee, O merciful Lord, to all thy faithful People pardon and peace, that they being cleanſed from all their ſins, may walk in bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly love and agreement of Mind, and ſerve thee with a quiet Mind, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="collect">
               <head>
                  <hi>COLLECT VII.</hi> For heavenly Hope and Confidence.</head>
               <p>O God, who never faileſt to help and govern them, whom thou doſt bring up in thy ſtedfaſt fear and love; grant, I beſeech thee, that I may lean only upon the hope of thy heavenly grace, and in all my troubles put my whole truſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in thy mercy, that thou being my Ruler and Guide, I may ſo paſs through things temporal, that I loſe not the things Eternal, but may obtain thy gracious Promiſes, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord and Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="collect">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:35571:19"/>
               <head>COLLECT VIII. <hi>To Conclude.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALmighty God, who haſt promiſed to hear the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions of them that ask in thy Son's name; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee mercifully to incline thine ears, now that in his name, I have made my Prayers and Supplications unto thee, and grant that thoſe things which I have faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully asked according to thy will, may be effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally obtained to the relief of my neceſſity, and to the ſetting forth of thy Glory, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="collect">
               <head>
                  <hi>COLLECT IX.</hi> For a Bleſſing.</head>
               <p>THE Lord fulfil the deſires and Prayers of thy humble Servant, as may be moſt expedient for me. The Lord bleſs and keep me in the day of Battel, in the hour of death, and in the time of Judgment: The Lord lift up the light of his Countenance upon me, and give me Peace both now and evermore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="collect">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:35571:19"/>
               <head>A <hi>COLLECT</hi> in caſe the <hi>Soldier</hi> be viſited with <hi>Sickneſs,</hi> or lie dangerouſly ill of his <hi>Wounds.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O Lord look down from Heaven, viſit and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me thy <note n="*" place="margin">As the caſe requires.</note> afflicted or wounded Servant, whom thou haſt made the object of thy heavy wrath and diſpleaſure for the puniſhment of my ſins, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie, I beſeech thee, this thy fatherly correction to me, that the ſenſe of my weakneſs may add ſtrength to my Faith, and ſeriouſneſs to my repentance; that if it ſhall be thy good pleaſure to reſtore me to my former health, I may lead the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of my life, in thy fear and to thy glory; or elſe give me grace ſo to take thy viſitation, that after this painful life ended, I may dwell with thee in life everlaſting, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:35571:20"/>
               <head>A Private Prayer for the Morning.</head>
               <p>O Lord God of Hoſts, who ruleſt over all the Kingdoms of the Earth, in whoſe Hands there is power and might, ſo that none is able to withſtand thee, look down from Heaven, and behold from the Habitation of thy Holineſs and Glory, upon me, and all the Camp of our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who lie before thee dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins; be thou pleaſed to quicken us all by thy heavenly grace and power, that we may ariſe from the Death of ſin, unto the Life of righteouſneſs; particularly be merciful unto me, (the unworthieſt of all thy Servants) give ear unto my Prayer, O God, and hide not thy ſelf from my ſupplication, who come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee with all humility and devotion of Soul and Body, imploring thy fatherly mercy and forgiveneſs of all thoſe grievous ſins and tranſgreſſions, which I do now confeſs before thee. <note n="*" place="margin">Here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect your particular ſins.</note> O cleanſe thou me from all my faults, waſh me in the Blood of that Immaculate Lamb, who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered up himſelf a Sacrifice for the ſins of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35571:20"/>the whole World, look upon the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the Bleſſed Jeſus, and let his ſaving power and efficacy plead pardon for my ſins; hear, O Lord, and forgive; give grace and ſtrength to thy Servant, that he may reform all the errors and miſcarriages of his former Life, and be renewed in the Spirit of a ſober Mind, to think, and do always thoſe things, that be righteous in thy ſight; Shew thy Pity and Compaſſion to this ſinful and divided Nation, wherein we live; pardon our great and crying ſins, prevent the wrath of thy terrible Judgments, and give us not over a prey unto the will of our Enemies; for thou art the hope of our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Saviour thereof in the time of trouble; and therefore, that we may enjoy ſecurity and reſt, from all our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies round about us, be thou pleaſed to bleſs and defend, with thy peculiar favour and providence, Their Sacred Majeſties, King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> make Them the ſaving Inſtruments of this Church and Nation; and to this end, do thou proſper Their Forces, both by Land and Sea, with happy Succeſs and Victory. Be thou, O Lord, the God of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and Salvation, in the Day of Battel, and ſtrengthen the Hands of our General, and bleſs all our Officers and Soldiers, that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35571:21"/>we may be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the Power of his might, to fight valiantly for the cauſe of God.</p>
               <p>And now, O Lord, leſt any unthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for former mercies, may make me uncapable of thy future favours: I deſire to praiſe and glorifie thy holy name for all thy Temporal and Spiritual Bleſſings, for the particular preſervations of thy good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, that thou haſt defended my life hitherto from the violence of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; and be thou pleaſed to continue ſtill watchful over me; help me. O God of my Salvation, for the glory of thy name; and let me not be delivered over into the Hands of mercileſs and cruel Men: and ſince I know not what ſudden dangers may encompaſs me, give me ſerious thoughts to prepare for the Hour of Death, and the Day of Judgment, that I may not be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized at any ſudden change or accident of mortality, but may patiently ſubmit to thy Holy Will, and whether I live or die, chearfully reſign both my Soul and Body into the Protection of thy good Providence, for the ſake of Chriſt Jeſus, who is the God of my hope and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in whom I will truſt for my deliverance from the Enemy; and therefore devoutly pray, as he hath taught me in his Holy Goſpel, ſaying, <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:35571:21"/>
               <head>A Private Prayer for the Evening.</head>
               <p>O Lord God, merciful and gracious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who beareſt the moſt tender love and compaſſion to the Children of Men; who hath no pleaſure in the death of the wicked, but rather that he ſhould turn from his way and live: Be graciouſly pleaſed to accept of the hearty Contrition and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of thy humble Servant, who meekly confeſs my ſins, and acknowledge my vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <note n="*" place="margin">Hear men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the ſins of the day.</note> I have ſinned againſt thee; O what ſhall I do unto thee? O thou preſerver of Men! I have indeed ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy Mercies and thy Judgments, againſt the checks of my own Conſcience, and the deliberate Vows and Purpoſes of Holy amendment; But now, O Father, I come unto thee, in the mercies of the Holy Jeſus, and pray thee, That thou wilt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the Sacrifice of his Blood to be a Propitiation for my ſins; O let the ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of that everlaſting Covenant waſh and purifie my Soul clean and undefiled from all the Pollutions of Vice and Wickedneſs, and do thou fill me with ſuch a Meaſure
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35571:22"/>and Portion of thy Grace, that I may reſiſt all future Temptations, and diligently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply my heart to fulfil all thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by ſerving thee in true Holineſs and Righteouſneſs all the days of my life; remember with me, the ſorrowful State and Condition of Mankind; ſhew thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and compaſſion to the manifold fins and Provocations of this Land and Nation, and puniſh us not according to our iniquities: for then how ſhall we eſcape, O God, if thou be extreme to mark what we have done amiſs? O remember not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us our former iniquities; but let thy tender mercies ſpeedily help and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent us, heal all our Diviſions and Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in Opinion, and unite us all by the bands of Brotherly Love and Charity, that we may become a choſen Generation, and a peculiar People zealous of Good Works. Let us not continue unthankful for thy late Mercies, but let us all, O Lord, conſider thy Work, and the power of thy Providence, and ſo repent of this our backſliding wickedneſs, that iniquity may not be out Ruine. And that Truth and Peace may flouriſh in our daies, bleſs the Supream Power and Government of Their Majeſties, King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> proſper thou the Great Work of Their Hands, O proſper thou Their handywork, that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35571:22"/>They may become Victorious over all Their Enemies; And to this end, give a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of ſtrength and courage to Their Forces, both by Land and Sea: particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I pray for the chief Commanders, the Officers and Soldiers of this <note n="*" place="margin">As occaſion requires.</note>
                  <hi>Camp</hi> or <hi>Gariſon;</hi> Give us all the Spirit of Chriſtian For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and Reſolution, that we may be ſtrong, and of good courage, to ſtand before the Enemy in the day of Battel; O preſerve thou the Life of thy Servant who now calls upon thee, let the Enemy have no advantage over me, nor the wicked approach to hurt me; but let me be continually guarded by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of thy good Providence until theſe Calamities be over-paſt. And as thou haſt been pleaſed to defend me this day, and all the days of my Life; (for which my Soul does praiſe and magnifie thy Holy Name, for this and all other thy mercies) ſo let no evil happen unto me this Night, nor any Deſtruction come nigh my Tent or Dwelling; but, O bleſſed Lord, the keeper of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who never ſlumbereſt nor ſleepeſt, watch over me, and all the Camp of our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that we may be ſecure from all dangers both of Soul and Body; Give me ſerious Apprehenſions of Death, that I may conſider the few and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35571:23"/>days of my Pilgrimage here: and ſince I know not how ſhort my time is to live, make me ſenſible of all the ſudden accidents and dangers of War, that I may never live in ſuch a ſtate, as I ſhall be afraid to die, but may be always ready with chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and joy to reſign my ſelf into the Hands of my merciful Redeemer; and grant, O Lord, that whether I ſleep or wake, live or die, I may always continue thy faithful Servant, even unto the end of my life; for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt my only Lord and Saviour, in whoſe Name I further call upon thee, ſaying,</p>
               <p>Our Father, which art in heaven, Hallowed be thy Name. Thy kingdom come. Thy will be done in earth, As it is in heaven. Give us this day our daily bread. And forgive us our treſpaſſes, As we forgive them that treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs againſt us. And lead us not into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; But deliver us from evil. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Apostles_Creed">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:35571:23"/>
               <head>Repeat the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> which is the right Confeſſion of your Chriſtian Faith.</head>
               <p>I Believe in God the Father Almighty, Maker of Heaven and Earth:</p>
               <p>And in Jeſus Chriſt his only Son our Lord, Who was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, Born of the Virgin Mary, Suffered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Pontius Pilate, Was crucified, dead, and buried: He deſcended into Hell; The third day he roſe again from the dead. He aſcended into Heaven, And ſitteth on the right hand of God the Father Almighty; From thence he ſhall come to judge the quick and the dead.</p>
               <p>I believe in the holy Ghoſt; The holy Catholick Church; The Communion of ſaints; The forgiveneſs of ſins; The reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the body, And the life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. Amen.</p>
               <q>—And this is the victory that overcometh the world, even our faith,
<bibl>
                     <hi>1 John 5.4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>That is the word of faith which we preach, that if thou ſhalt confeſs with thy mouth the Lord Jeſus, and believe in thy heart, that God hat raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 10.8, 9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="Ten_Commandments">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:35571:24"/>
               <head>Repeat often the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> or the <hi>Ten Commandments,</hi> which is the Rule of your Obedience.</head>
               <p>GOD ſpake theſe words and ſaid, I am the Lord thy God: Thou ſhalt have none other Gods but me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, have mercy upon me, and incline my heart to keep this law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven image, nor the likeneſs of any thing that is in heaven above, or in the earth beneath, or in the water under the earth. Thou ſhalt not bow down to them, nor worſhip them: for I the Lord thy God am a jealous God, and viſit the ſins of the fathers upon the children, unto the third and fourth generation of them that hate me; and ſhew mercy unto thouſands in them that love me, and keep my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, have mercy upon me, and incline my heart to keep this law.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:35571:24"/>
               <p>Thou ſhalt not take the Name of the Lord thy God in vain: for the Lord will not hold him guiltleſs that taketh his Name in vain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, have mercy upon me, and incline my heart to keep this law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Remember that thou keep holy the Sabbath day. Six days ſhalt thou labour, and do all that thou haſt to do; but the ſeventh day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God. In it thou ſhalt do no manner of work, thou, and thy ſon, and thy daughter, thy man-ſervant, and thy maid-ſervant, thy cattel, and the ſtranger that is within thy gates. For in ſix days the Lord made heaven and earth, the ſea, and all that in them is, and reſted the ſeventh day: wherefore the Lord bleſſed the ſeventh day, and hallowed it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, have mercy upon me, and incline my heart to keep this law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Honour thy father and thy mother, that thy days may be long in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, have mercy upon me, and incline my heart to keep this law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt do no murther.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, have mercy upon me, and incline my heart to keep this law.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:35571:25"/>
               <p>Thou ſhalt not commit adultery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, have mercy upon me, and incline my heart to keep this law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt not ſteal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, have mercy upon me, and incline my heart to keep this law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs againſt thy neighbour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, have mercy upon me, and incline my heart to keep this law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt not covet thy neighbours houſe, thou ſhalt not covet thy neighbours wife, nor his ſervant, nor his maid, nor his ox, nor his aſs, nor any thing that is his.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, have mercy upon me, and write all theſe thy laws in my heart, I beſeech thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>—Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul, and with all thy mind. This is the firſt and great commandment. And the ſecond is like unto it, Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf. On theſe two commandments hang all the law and the prophets.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 22.</hi> v. <hi>37, 38, 39, 40.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="Pater_Noster">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:35571:25"/>
               <head>The <hi>Lord's Prayer</hi> the beſt form of your Chriſtian <hi>Devotion,</hi> either for the beginning or end of your Prayers.</head>
               <p>OUR Father which art in Heaven; Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed be thy Name. Thy Kingdom come. Thy will be done in earth, as it is in heaven. Give us this day our daily bread. And forgive us our treſpaſſes, As we forgive them that treſpaſs againſt us. And lead us not into temptation: But de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us from evil. For thine is the kingdom, The power and the glory, for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>After this manner therefore pray ye, Our Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 6.</hi> v. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>When the Soldier ſtands Sentinel.</head>
               <p>Take ye heed, watch and pray; for ye know not when the time is, <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.33.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:35571:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>When he goes out to</hi> mount <hi>or</hi> diſmount <hi>the Guard.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Lord preſerve my going out and my coming in, from this time forth and for evermore, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121. <hi>v.</hi> 8.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>When he goes to fight the Enemy.</head>
               <p>Plead thou my cauſe, O Lord, with them that ſtrive with me: and fight thou againſt them, that fight againſt thee. Take hold of ſhield and buckler, and ſtand up for mine help, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35. <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2.</p>
               <p>¶ <hi>God be with you in your life, and at your death, and make your Soul and Body pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in the ſight of the Lord; with whom, I pray, that you may live for evermore.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
